David Wright

davidwwright.netlify.com



dave.w.wright



+44 7412 459009



dww100



davewwright



dave.william.wright@gmail.com

About Me ——

I am a molecular modeller and software engineer, with a wide range of problem solving skills and experience running and maintaining IT infrastructure. I have also led small development teams and collaborated in large multi-national projects.

Skills ———

Molecular Simulation

High Performance Computing

Programming: Python, R, Fortran, C

Data Analysis

Presentation Delivery

Project Management

System Administration

Containerization: Docker, Singularity

Cloud: Kubernetes, Azure, AWS, Google

References —

Available upon request

Experience

I have fulfilled a variety of roles in my postdoctoral career, combining both modelling and software development, published 29 articles in leading journals and conference proceedings (a list of which are provided below). I have presented work at major conferences such as the Biophysical Society Annual Meeting, in 2012, 2013 and 2015, and International Supercomputing Conference (ISC) in 2018. During this time I have additionally worked on industrial projects on a consultancy basis.

2016 - present Research Associate

Centre for Computational Science, UCL

- Develop molecular simulation approaches to predict the strength of small molecule binding to protein targets for drug discovery applications.
- Process and analyze large quantities of simulation, experimental and clinical data.
- Lead team of developers on BAC 2.0 tool designed to automate molecular simulations using multiple applications and HTBAC workflow management tool.
- Lead development of the EasyVVUQ tool to automate verification, validation and uncertainty quantification for high performance computing applications.
- Research representative on the UCL Research Data Repository project board, involving collating and communicating user needs and providing feedback on project design and implementation.
- Contribute to reviews and panels informing strategic decisions in the European HPC (through the EXDCI project and PRACE scientific steering committee).
- Supervision of Masters and Ph.D. students, including both day to day direction of research, deadline management and coordination with primary supervisors.
- Organization of the "Free Energy Calculations from Molecular Simulation" workshop - in collaboration with the CompBioMed and BioExcel projects.
- Named investigator on the INSPIRE project (supported by the US department of INCITE program) combining molecular dynamics and machine learning to study cancer drug resistance.
- Contributing to writing of grant proposals, including those successfully approved for the CompBioMed2 (€8m) and VECMA (€4m) EU projects.

2017 - present Chief Scientific Officer

EnsembleMD

- Development and deployment of cloud based (SaaS) molecular simulation tools for multiple providers.
- Structural modelling of antibodies from small angle scattering data for pharmaceutical companies.
- Liaise with clients to determine their requirements and design solutions to fulfill them.

2013 - 2016 Research Associate

Structural Immunology Group, UCL

- Modelling and simulation of antibodies and other immune system proteins with the aim of understanding structural data.
- Lead developer of SCT, a Python package for the comparison of atomistic models to small angle scattering data.
- Head UK developer within the joint UK-US project CCP-SAS. Developed structural modelling packages (PDBRx, PDBScan), and contributed to underlying libraries (SASSIE, SasMol) and a common web interface for all project software (made available at sassieweb.chem.utk.edu).
- Trained users in the use of CCP-SAS tools, including teaching at a summer school at ILL in Grenoble, France.

1101

- Use of molecular dynamics simulations to understand the influence of protein mutations on drug binding.
- Administrator for network of 12 desktop machines and small cluster.
- Liaison with experimental groups in multinational medical and experimental project (CHAIN).

2010 - 2011 Biomedical Simulation Consultant

Dh D Chamistry

- Creation and testing of high performance computing workflow tools for Louisiana State University.
- Development (C and Fortran) of advanced simulation software for Fujitsu Laboratories of Europe.

Education

2011

2011	Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Drug Resistance in HIV-1 Protease and Reverse Transcriptase Advisor: Prof. Peter V. Coveney	UCL
2006	M Res (Distinction), CoMPLEX Modelling Biological Complexity	UCL
2003	M Phys (1st). Computational Physics	University of York

Publications

A live list of my publications can be found on **Google scholar**.

- J. Dakka, M. Turilli, **D. W. Wright** *et al.*, High-throughput binding affinity calculations at extreme scales, BMC Bioinformatics, 2018, 19 (18), DOI: 10.1186/s12859-018-2506-6
- W. Zhang, S. C. Howell, **D. W. Wright** *et al.*, Combined Monte Carlo/torsion-angle molecular dynamics for ensemble modeling of proteins, nucleic acids and carbohydrates, Journal of Molecular Graphics and Modelling, 2017, 73, DOI: 10.1016/j.jmgm.2017.02.010
- N. A. Altwaijry, M. Baron, **D. W. Wright** *et al.*, An Ensemble-Based Protocol for the Computational Prediction of Helix–Helix Interactions in G Protein-Coupled Receptors using Coarse-Grained Molecular Dynamics, Journal of chemical theory and computation, 2017, 13 (5), DOI: 10.1021/acs.jctc.6b01246
- R. Nan, C. M. Furze, **D. W. Wright** *et al.*, Flexibility in mannan-binding lectin-associated serine proteases-1 and-2 provides insight on lectin pathway activation, Structure, 2017, 25 (2), DOI: 10.1016/j.str.2016.12.014
- A. P. Bhati, S. Wan, **D. W. Wright** and P. V. Coveney, Rapid, accurate, precise, and reliable relative free energy prediction using ensemble based thermodynamic integration, Journal of chemical theory and computation, 2016, 13 (1), DOI: 10.1021/acs.jctc.6b00979
- S. J. Perkins, **D. W. Wright**, H. Zhang *et al.*, Atomistic modelling of scattering data in the Collaborative Computational Project for Small Angle Scattering (CCP-SAS), Journal of applied crystallography, 2016, 49 (6), DOI: 10.1107/S160057671601517X
- K. W. Fung, **D. W. Wright**, J. Gor *et al.*, Domain structure of human complement C4b extends with increasing NaCl concentration: implications for its regulatory mechanism, Biochemical Journal, 2016, 473 (23), DOI: 10.1042/BCJ20160744

- G. K. Hui, **D. W. Wright**, O. L. Vennard *et al*, The solution structures of native and patient monomeric human IgA1 reveal asymmetric extended structures: implications for function and IgAN disease, Biochemical Journal, 2015, 471 (2), DOI: 10.1042/BJ20150612
- S. Wan, B. Knapp, **D. W. Wright** *et al.*, "Rapid, Precise, and Reproducible Prediction of Peptide–MHC Binding Affinities from Molecular Dynamics That Correlate Well with Experiment", Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation, 2015, 11 (7), DOI: 10.1021/acs.jctc.5b00179
- **D. W. Wright** and S. J. Perkins, SCT: a suite of programs for comparing atomistic models with small-angle scattering data, *Journal of Applied Crystallography*, 2015, 48 (3), DOI: 10.1107/S1600576715007062
- J. B. Swadling, **D. W. Wright**, J. L. Suter and P. V. Coveney, Structure, Dynamics, and Function of the Hammerhead Ribozyme in Bulk Water and at a Clay Mineral Surface from Replica Exchange Molecular Dynamics, Langmuir 31 (8), 2493-2501, DOI: 10.1021/la503685t
- I. P. Deuzing, C. Charpentier, **D. W. Wright** *et al.*, Mutation V111I in HIV-2 reverse transcriptase increases the fitness of the nucleoside analogue resistant K65R and Q151M viruses, *Journal of Virology*, 2014, 89 (1), 833-843, DOI: 10.1128/JVI.02259-14
- **D. W. Wright**, B. A. Hall, Owain A. Kenway, Shantenu Jha and P. V. Coveney, Computing Clinically Relevant Binding Free Energies of HIV-1 Protease Inhibitors, *Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation*, 2014, 10 (3), DOI: 10.1021/ct4007037
- M. B. A. Kunze, **D. W. Wright**, N. D. Werbeck, J. Kirkpatrick, P. V. Coveney, and D. F. Hansen, Loop Interactions and Dynamics Tune the Enzymatic Activity of the Human Histone Deacetylase 8, *Journal of the American Chemical Society*, 2013, 135 (47), DOI: 10.1021/ct4007037
- **D. W. Wright**, I. P. Deuzing, P. Flandre, P. van den Eede, M. Govaert, L. Setiawan, P. V. Coveney, A. Marcelin, V. Calvez, C. A. B. Boucher, N. Beerens, A Polymorphism at Position 400 in the Connection Subdomain of HIV-1 Reverse Transcriptase Affects Sensitivity to NNRTIs and RNaseH Activity, *PLoS One*, 2013, DOI: 10.1371/journal.pone.0074078
- **D. W. Wright**, S. K. Sadiq, G. De Fabritiis and P. V. Coveney, Thumbs down for HIV: Domain level rearrangements do occur in the NNRTI bound HIV-1 Reverse Transcriptase, *Journal of the American Chemical Society*, 2012, 134 (31), DOI: 10.1021/ja301565k
- S. Wan, **D. W. Wright** and P.V. Coveney, Mechanism of Drug Efficacy Within the EGF Receptor Revealed by Microsecond Molecular Dynamics Simulation, *Molecular Cancer Therapeutics*, 2012, 11, DOI: 10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-12-0644-T
- B. A. Hall, **D. W. Wright**, S. Jha and P. V. Coveney, Quantized water access to the HIV-1 protease active site as a mechanism for cooperative changes in drug affinity, *Biochemistry*, 2012, 51 (33), DOI: 10.1021/bi300432u
- **D. W. Wright**, B. A. Hall, P. Kellam and P. V. Coveney, Global Conformational Dynamics of HIV-1 Reverse Transcriptase Bound to Non Nucleoside Inhibitors, *Biology*, 2012, 1(2), DOI: 10.3390/biology1020222
- **D. W. Wright**, S. Wan, N. Shublaq, S. Zasada and P. V. Coveney, From base pair to bedside: molecular simulation and the translation of genomics to personalised medicine, *WIREs Systems Biology and Medicine*, 2012, 4, 6, DOI: 10.1002/wsbm.1186
- **D. W. Wright** and P. V. Coveney, Resolution of Discordant HIV-1 Protease Resistance Rankings Using Molecular Dynamics Simulations, *Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling*, 2011, 51, DOI: 10.1021/ci200308r
- R. S. Saksena, B. Boghosian, L. Fazendeiro, O. A. Kenway, S. Manos, M. D. Mazzeo, S. K. Sadiq, J. L. Suter, **D. W. Wright** and P. V. Coveney, Real Science at the Petascale, *Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A*, 2009, 367, DOI: 10.1098/rsta.2009.0049

Preprints

- S. K. Sadiq, **D. W. Wright**, O. A. Kenway and P. V. Coveney, Accurate Ensemble Molecular Dynamics Binding Free Energy Ranking of Multidrug-Resistant HIV-1 Proteases, *Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling*, 2009, 50, DOI: 10.1021/ci100007w
- S. K. Sadiq, **D. W. Wright**, S. J. Watson, S. J. Zasada, I. Stoica, and P. V. Coveney, Automated Molecular Simulation-Based Binding Affinity Calculator for Ligand-Bound HIV-1 Proteases, *Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling*, 2008, 48, DOI: 10.1021/ci8000937
- **D. W. Wright**, S. Wan, C. Meyer *et al.*, Application of ESMACS Binding Free Energy Protocols to Diverse Datasets: Bromodomain-Containing Protein 4, ChemRxiv (submitted to Scientific Reports) DOI: 10.26434/chemrxiv.7327019.v1
- **D. W. Wright**, E. L. K. Ellison, G. K. Hui and S. J. Perkins, Monte Carlo atomistic modelling of X-ray and neutron scattering data for human IgG1 and IgG4 reveals new insights on antibody solution structure and function, submitted to Biophysical Journal

Conference Proceedings and Posters

- **D. W. Wright**, G. K. Hui, O. L. Vennard, L. E. Rayner *et al.*, The asymmetric solution structures of native and patient monomeric human IgA1 reveal new insights on IgA nephropathy, 2015, *SAS 2015*
- **D. W. Wright**, G. K. Hui, O. L. Vennard, L. E. Rayner *et al.*, The asymmetric solution structures of native and patient monomeric human IgA1 reveal new insights on IgA nephropathy, 2015, *SAS 2015*
- **D. W. Wright**, R. Nan, G. Hui, J. E. Curtis, E. H. Brookes and S. J. Perkins, CCP-SAS Novel Approaches for the Atomistic Modelling of Small Angle Scattering Data in Biology, 2015, *Biophysical Society 59th Annual Meeting*
- **D. W. Wright**, Novel approaches for the atomistic modelling of small angle scattering data in biology, 2015, *CCP-Biosim 2015 Annual Conference*
- **D. W. Wright**, S. K. Sadiq, G. De Fabritiis and P. V. Coveney, Thumbs down to HIV: Domain level rearrangements do occur in the NNRTI bound HIV-1 Reverse Transcriptase, 2012, *Biophysical Society 56th Annual Meeting* (Poster)
- **D. W. Wright**, B. A. Hall, S. Jha and P. V. Coveney, Multiscale Modelling of the Interplay Between Global and Local Structural Changes in Viral Drug Target Proteins, 2012, *VPH2012*
- O. Kenway, **D. W. Wright**, H. Heller *et al.* Towards high-throughput, high-performance computational estimation of binding affinities for patient specific HIV-1 protease sequences, *Proceedings of the 2011 TeraGrid Conference on Extreme Digital Discovery TG '11*, DOI: 10.1145/2016741.2016746
- P. V. Coveney, **D. W. Wright** and S. K. Sadiq, Rapid and Accurate Binding Free Energy Prediction for Inhibitor-Bound HIV-1 Enzymes, 2010, *Biophysical Society 53rd Annual Meeting* (Poster)
- **D. W. Wright**, S. K. Sadiq, O. Kenway *et al.* Computational Estimation of Binding Affinities for Patient Derived HIV-1 Protease Sequences Bound to Lopinavir, *VPH2010*, http://www.vphnoe.eu/vphrepository/doc_download/204-bookofabstractsforvph2010
- S. Wan, **D. W. Wright**, S. K. Zasada and P. V. Coveney, Personalized Drug Ranking in Clinical Decision Support, *VPH2010*, http://www.vphnoe.eu/vphrepository/doc_download/204bookofabstractsforvph2010
- I have presented work at major conferences such as the Biophysical Society Annual Meeting, in 2012, 2013 and 2015, and International Supercomputing Conference (ISC) in 2018.